there are so many benefits to doing
intermitted fasting but there's also the
dark side which I want to talk about too
the benefits are weight loss cognitive
improvements Focus attention memory or
heart issue or whatever you're going to
find those will probably be a lot better
but here's a thing you need to know
about intermittent fasting okay you're
avoiding food for a period of time and
most of the things I'm going to talk
about are not related necessarily to a
16 or 17 or 18 hour fast I'm talking
about when you do prolong fasting let's
say you're doing it for 48 hours 72 or
even longer this information applies
more to that situation all right so
here's the thing the purpose of food is
to not just get fuel for your body it's
to get nutrients from the food so if you
are not eating because you're fasting
okay you're restricting nutrients and if
your diet is not providing add ing all
the nutrients okay you can end up with
not just deficiencies but what's called
subclinical nutrition deficiencies and
that can set you up for a lot of
problems so virtually all the things I'm
going to talk about are related to that
one point so let's first talk about the
first one it's called refeeding syndrome
so let's say you do this uh I don't know
three or four or five day fast okay and
then you eat this huge meal not a good
idea especially if you eat a
carbohydrate meal and you have some type
of pre-existing nutritional deficiency
because this could be dangerous and you
can have a lot of problems it's always
good and safe when you come off a fast
to just have a little bit of food wait
for a couple hours eat a little bit more
and I wouldn't do carbohydrates I would
do a little protein maybe an egg or a
little bit of salad wait a little bit
maybe have some nuts an avocado things
like that but don't do what I did I mean
I was just like because I didn't eat for
a long period of time I overcompensated
I just ate a ton ton of food and I felt
really good for about a minute and then
I'm like oh my gosh I don't feel too
good I feel really sick my body from not
eating just wasn't used to that much
food so break your fast with a smaller
meal and gradually come out of it I will
put a link down below for more details
on that thing but this refeeding
syndrome problem usually occurs if you
know maybe you have a problem with
anorexia or you're chronic alcoholic or
you have some type of malabsorption
issue where you don't get enough
nutrition because you have um
inflammatory issues in your gut or
you're elderly or you have advanced
diabetes or even you're on certain
medications like an acids or diuretics
that deplete you of certain nutrients or
you just basically have a low vitamin B1
deficiency so that's when you start
having problems with the refeeding
syndrome because we have this shift of
fluid and electrolytes from inside the
cell to the blood all right so that's
number one number two dirty keto which
is basically you're doing low carb but
you're not looking at the quality of the
food you're not looking at nutrients and
like I said before it's always this
nutritional deficiency problem because
when you eat junk food even if it's low
carb junk food the quality is not there
the nutrition is not there it can set
you up for more problems because you're
not eating and you're restricting these
uh nutrients even more like for example
zinc um your body has enough stored zinc
to last like 4 days well let's say you
don't get enough zinc from the diet
which a lot of people don't and then
here you are going into this fastest
situation and then you just magnify that
deficiency and a zinc deficiency can
show up as a weakness within your immune
system it can affect your taste it can
affect your vision it can affect your
skin it can affect your stomach like
gastritis things like that all right
number three not taking nutrients while
you're fasting I always recommend taking
at least at a bare minimum electrolytes
trace minerals and B vitamins but the
point is if you don't take these
electrolytes and I'm also talking about
sea salt and your fasting especially 2 3
four 5 days you might have issues like
feeling faint dizzy heard about people
just passed out and also when you're
either on the ketogenic diet or you do
intermittent fasting you're running on
ketones running on ketones increases the
demand for certain nutrients like uh
vitamin B1 and other B vitamins and even
potassium which means you can also end
up with something like keto fatigue or
keto rash or just weakness in general
all right number four kidney stones
kidney stones can occur for several
reasons the most common one is uric acid
stones and let's say for example you're
doing a ketogenic diet you're doing
intermittent fasting typically people
eat a lot of almonds right and they
might do some non- sugar chocolate or
they also might do spinach all three of
those are are very high in oxalates and
if you're predisposed to kidney stones
that can make it worse I would
definitely avoid those Foods if you have
a tendency to get kidney stones I would
also take lemon juice in your water and
drink enough water like 2 and a half
liters of fluid a day and that alone
should prevent kidney stones now the
other type of kidney stones is uric acid
Stones it is true when you do long fast
your uric acid goes up okay and then it
comes down and stabilizes that that's
not a pathogenic problem because uric
acid is probably one of the most potent
antioxidants in your blood and so it
does it mean that you're going to have
gout or some type of U arthritis no it
just means when you do a fast you may
have um certain chemistry changes
occurring and one really good thing for
uric acid just to kind of counter it
when you eventually eat make sure you
have big salads which I always recommend
to kind of flesh out any Ty type of uh
uric acid that might be concentrating
now this may become a problem if with a
person doing uh carnivore but I have not
really seen that being a problem somehow
the body compensates and they don't seem
to have uh more problems with gout they
have less problems with gout even though
they're doing a lot of animal protein
which is interesting number five if
you're anorexic you're going to have
nutritional deficiencies so when you do
intermittent fasting it's going to
create more of a problem so I don't
recommend in a minute fasting if you're
Bic or anorexic um but I do recommend
the ketogenic diet for sure but not
prolong fasting number six athletes that
have not adapted to Fat yet okay so in
this process of getting on keto you
start adapting to keto which within like
three days but then it actually takes
one to three months to fully adapt to
your fat metabolism right so to be fat
adapted takes a lot longer than what you
might think so in the process and you're
working out you may not have adapted to
Fat so when you exercise you might kind
of have energy and then kind of come
down um but I will say over time uh
there are athletes that have adapted to
this fat over a period of months and man
they can burn fat three times better
than anyone else they can just go go go
so the point is that you have to give it
more time and in the process of this
adaptation you might want to adjust your
workouts and training maybe right after
you eat until you can fully fat adapt
just as a side note too uh if you're an
athlete and you're exercising and you
don't have enough sea salt your muscles
will be weak okay also uh potassium is
very very important as well number seven
if you're a child okay not the best idea
to do any type of prolonged fasting now
let's say you're a teenager overweight
like let's say you're obese well maybe
you would just do like two meals but I
would definitely start cutting out the
snacking I don't agree with this
snacking all day long but the point is
if you have three solid meals with a
child and they're nutrient-dense I mean
that's what you want to do why because
what we're trying to do is prevent
nutritional
deficiencies and it is more difficult to
get nutrients from food nowadays I mean
even going in the grocery store most of
the lettuces that you eat are hydroponic
and I do have a problem with that
because they only put 15 minerals in
there and they're kind of bland they
tasteless I really don't think they have
the same nutrients as salad that's grown
on soil all right number eight nutrition
is most important when you're pregnant
and when you're lactating because you're
eating for two and you're providing milk
and your body is becoming depleted just
a deficiency of vitamin D can set your
child up for all sorts of dental
malformations which then caus the need
for braces down the road or they might
have an overbite or an underbite or they
might have flat feet or bod legs all of
these things can be easily solved if
that mother has enough of the right
nutrients also realize that most of the
prenatals out there are all synthetic
get a whole food natural prenatal and
especially take it when you're
breastfeeding as well and one more point
about infant formulas and baby food
unfortunately it's like ultr processed
food if you look at the ingredients it
doesn't even resemble real food
unfortunately so um there are some
Alternatives I will put a link down
below of what I recommend for um for
children like baby food that's actually
much better number nine if you have a
loss of muscle let's say for example
you're older and you're starting to
develop muscle loss and you're doing in
a minute fasting I recommend adding one
additional nutrient a blend of amino
acids that can actually give you this
raw material without creating a problem
of it turning into sugar but it can
actually Supply the muscles to prevent a
loss of muscle and if you're taking the
other nutrients like the B vitamins and
electrolytes you allow these amino acids
to be formed as muscle because all the
biochemistry all the requirements for uh
the enzymes mostly they're just protein
and this goes beyond the Protein that's
needed for fossil ligament tendon fascia
connective tissue all of those protein
molecules need co-actors and co-enzymes
and those are the vitamins and minerals
so we come full circle to these
nutrients right so I'm trying to really
emphasize that one point and then number
10 keto
acidosis if you look up the dangers of
fasting if you look up the dangers of um
keto you will see this word keeps coming
up this is a situation where you have
too much ketones going in your body and
too many ketones are producing an
acidity in your blood which can be very
very dangerous okay but there's so much
confusion I want to just clarify this
right now you have physiological ketosis
okay and you also have keto acidosis
they're not the same at all the point is
that keto acidosis is very rare unless
you have the following condition s
uncontrolled diabetes where you have
type one diabetes sometimes type two
you're taking insulin and you forgot to
take your insulin in type one you have
the cells of the pancreas that have just
basically stopped producing insulin okay
so what's going to happen to your blood
sugars they're going to go very very
high because you have no insulin to
monitor that or or regulate that but
insulin also controls ketones and so
insulin suppresses ketones and if you
have no more insulin you have this
massive flush or generation of ketones
so your body starts burning fat like
crazy and you have very high levels
above 10 11 or 12 levels of ketones now
typically when you do the physiological
ketones which you're this is a natural
process you restrict carbohydrates and
usually you're going to go between 0.5
to three I haven't seen many people go
over five or even six and to do that you
have to do prolonged fasting and
exercise but the great majority of
people are going to be three I mean this
is a very far range from 10 okay so
uncontrolled
diabetes if you're a chronic alcoholic
okay you could have the same problem if
you're on certain medications like high
levels of aspirin can create this
situation even certain drugs like
cocaine for example you can go into this
keto acidosis when you abuse uh cocaine
or there's other conditions like chronic
liver disease right where the liver um
is very very damaged and on top of that
you're a diabetic that can create a
problem as well or even if you're um
pregnant malnutrition so as you can see
there are conditions that can make you
more vulnerable to this keto acidosis
but it's very very rare the physiologic
ketosis okay is not pathogenic it's
extremely healthy and there's huge
benefits if anyone says that ketosis is
is toxic just ask them about what about
glucotoxicity right that's high carbs
that's high sugar what is that that's
like all the bad effects from diabetes
because you're have massively high sugar
what about the dangers of that and also
think about this one last Point keto
acidosis usually originates because
you're eating too many carbs you're not
doing low carb you're eing high carbs
destroys the pancreas and then you get
keto Aid dois so anyway I just wanted to
cover these points the next point is if
you now want to know how to do inent
fasting correctly you should watch this
video right
here